A register of the Aleksandr Il'ich Ginzburg Papers, 1921-2007
Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksandr Il'ich Ginzburg papers
1921-2007
2004C55
Ginzburg, Aleksandr Il'ich, 1936-
18 manuscript boxes, 10 cassette boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 card file box (19 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Materials relating to civil liberties and dissent in the Soviet Union and to Russian émigré affairs including correspondence, writings, printed matter, identification documents, photographs, sound and video recordings, printed matter, and memorabilia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2004, with several increments received in 2005, 2007, and 2011
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital reproductions of selected images are available
Related Collections
A. SiniavskiĬ papers, Hoover Institution Archives
RFE/RL broadcast records, Hoover Institution Archives
Yuri Yarim-Agaev papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Leon Volkov papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Natal'ia Solzhenitsyn speech, Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksandr Isaevich Solzhenitsyn speeches and writings, Hoover Institution Archives
Irina Kaplun writings, Hoover Institution Archives
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Ginzburg, Arina; Dissenters--Soviet Union; Russians--France; Civil rights--Soviet Union; Phonotapes
Biographical Note
1936 November 21 Born in Moscow, Soviet Union
1956-1960 Studied at the Moscow State University, Department of Journalism
1959 Edited and distributed first three issues of the Sintaksis underground literary almanac
1960 July Arrested and sentenced to a two-year term in a correctional labor institution in Kirovskaia oblast'
1964 Arrested and imprisoned for several months for distribution of New Class book by Milovan Djilas
1966 Admitted to the Historical-Archival Institute, Moscow Compiled "Belaia kniga"(White book) about the court trial of writers AndreĬ SiniavskiĬ and IUliĬ Daniel'
1967 Arrested, charged with anti-Soviet propaganda and agitation, and sentenced to a five-year camp term, which he partly served in Pot'ma, Mordovia, and partly in the strict regime Vladimirskaia prison
1972 Released from camp, prohibited from residence in Moscow, lived in exile in Tarusa
1974 Administrator of the Solzhenitsyn Fund for Aid to Political Prisoners
1976 May 12 Co-founder of the Moscow Helsinki Group (MHG)
1977 Arrested, along with other members of the MHG Aleksandr Ginzburg Defence Committee is established in the U.S.
1978 July 13 Tried in Kaluga and sentenced to an eight-year strict regime camp term, which he served in the Dubrovlag system in Mordovia
1979 Released and exchanged, along with three other political prisoners, for Soviet spies in the United States
1979-1980 Lectured at universities in the United States Family joined him in the United States
1980 Moved to France
1982-probably 1988 Head of the Russian Cultural Center in Montgeron
1988-1997 Columnist, Russkaia mysl' newspaper
2002 Died in Paris, France
Scope and Content Note
The documents in the Aleksandr Ginzburg papers portray him as a fighter for freedom and human rights, a person of culture and integrity. They also show how Aleksandr Ginzburg was persecuted by Soviet authorities and how he was finally sent into exile abroad. His wife, Arina (Irina) Ginzburg, provided documents with extensive comments and explanations, which complement Ginzburg's papers.
The Biographical file documents three imprisonments of Aleksandr Ginzburg, his exile, and rehabilitation. Ginzburg was first arrested in 1960 for his attempt to publish an uncensored magazine, Sintaksis, which included works of writers unacceptable to official publishers. The trial materials, including a letter from the prominent writer IUriĬ Olesha confiscated during Ginzburg's arrest, were returned to the family in the 1990s. Trial documents allow researchers to understand the "rule of law" in the Soviet Union. Arina Ginzburg, along with their friend Vera Lashkova, attended Ginzburg's third trial in the city of Kaluga and made notes about it; their account is included in the Biographical file. At the time of that trial, friends and family were waiting outside the court building; they were secretly photographed by another friend, Viktor Timachev (see the Photographs). Also most informative is Arina's logbook (also in Electronic documents), in which she meticulously listed the contents of her letters to her husband and other prisoners in the Pot'ma camp and their responses, food purchased for camp visits, and other events in her life.
Aleksandr Ginzburg's fight for human rights and his three imprisonments brought wide attention abroad. The Alexander Ginzburg Defense Committee petitioned the Soviet and United States governments and organized demonstrations fighting for his release, which are documented in the Biographical file. Of special interest in the Biographical file are materials relating to the dismissal of Aleksandr and Arina from Russkaia mysl' by chief editor Irina IlovaĬskaia-Alberti, including their comprehensive account of the dismissal and many letters from public figures in Russia protesting it.
Correspondence includes letters addressed to Arina and Aleksandr Ginzburg from many dissidents and prominent public figures, including AndreĬ Sakharov, Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, Natal'ia Solzhenitsyna, Vladimir BukovskiĬ, Natal'ia Gorbanevskaia, to name just a few, and letters they received as Russkaia mysl' newspaper employees (these are mostly letters from writers and other intellectuals).
Speeches and writings includes excerpts from Aleksandr Ginzburg's unfinished memoirs, his essays about AndreĬ Sakharov and the writer Bulat Okudzhava, and his interviews by Raisa Orlova, Annie Tchernychev, SergeĬ Kovalev, and others.
"Zeks," a play by Maria Rasa, in the Writings by others, was based on a real incident that happened to Aleksandr Ginzburg in the forced labor camp in Mordovia. The play was staged at the Theater for the New City, directed by Jonas JuraŠaŠ. Photographic prints depicting Aleksandr Ginzburg with the director and actors after the performance, included in the same folder, supplement the script.
Also included in the Writings by others is a holograph Samizdat book with several poems by Igor Severianin copied by Aleksandr Ginzburg; the hand-made book traveled with him to prisons and camps. Unpublished recollections of Filip Makhonin about his meetings with the prominent writer Viktor Nekrasov are accompanied by photographs and Makhonin's illustrations to Nekrasov's book V okopakh Stalingrada.
In the Subject file researchers will find clippings and documents that bring to light dissident activities. Particularly illustrative material is contained in the Dronnikov-Konovalov sets of portrait sketches depicting Ginzburg and the writers Vladimir Maksimov, AndreĬ SiniavskiĬ, and Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn. In 1973-1974 Solzhenitsyn established a Fund for Aid to Political Prisoners and Their Families (later called the Solzhenitsyn Fund), and Aleksandr Ginzburg became its first administrator. Also in the Subject file are materials relating to the war in Chechnia, which Aleksandr Ginzburg followed closely.
A reprint in Grani of the previously mentioned Sintaksis, magazine and a tiny edition (to be smuggled into the Soviet Union) of Solzhenitsyn's Arkhipelag Gulag are worth mentioning among other interesting publications in the Printed matter.
Materials relating to the establishment of the Russkaia mysl' Moscow Bureau, especially letters in support of publication and distribution of the newspaper in Russia from Elena Bonner, Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, the politician Galina Starovoitova, and others, are among the most interesting documents in the Russkaia mysl' file.
Hundreds of photographic prints in the Photographs series present a comprehensive picture of the life of dissidents in the 1970s and 1980s, their gatherings, and travels to prisons, camps, and exile. On the reverse of some photogaphs are letters to Aleksandr Ginzburg in prison from his wife and his mother Liudmila. Several unique photographs depict Solzhenitsyn's apartment after his family left the Soviet Union and his car donated to the Solzhenitsyn Fund. In the late 1980s and early 1990s, after the fall of the Iron Curtain, Ginzburg's home in Paris attracted visitors from Russia; many photographs depict Aleksandr and Arina Ginzburg with writers, singers, actors, film and stage directors, and political figures.
The most important among the Electronic documents are Aleksandr and Arina Ginzburg's correspondence during his imprisonments and the previously mentioned logbook of Arina Ginzburg, which was confiscated during his arrest. It was returned to Arina in the 1990s, with a page from the trial file given to Arina by mistake. The page contained KGB notes with secret (coded) names for Ginzburg, Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, Natal'ia Solzhenitsyna, and others. These documents were scanned by the Ginzburg family, who retain the originals.
Among the Sound and video recordings one compact sound cassette contains a recording of IUliĬ Daniel reading poetry written by another prisoner, Kurt Skujenieks, which Ginzburg managed to record in the camp and smuggle abroad; later the recording was aired by Radio Liberty to the great surprise of KGB officials. The Sound and video recordings include 429 compact audio cassettes and 18 videotape cassettes. 130 audio cassettes contain the Ginzburg McGoff lecture series, recorded telephone conversations of Aleksandr Ginzburg with his Moscow correspondents, interviews of cultural and political figures, news from all over the world, etc. These tapes were a source of information for Ginzburg's "News from the Motherland" weekly column in Russkaia mysl'. Four cassettes (nos. 26, 30, 35, and 46) have not been delivered to the Hoover Archives. One compact cassette (no. 31) has not been described. (Arina Ginzburg compiled a list of the cassettes, with detailed descriptions of their content.) Another 299 audiocassettes record uncensored Soviet/Russian underground poetry and songs; among the authors are Joseph Brodsky, Aleksandr Galich, Bulat Okudzhava, IUliĬ Kim, Vladimir Vysotsky, and many others.
A U.S. one-dollar bill was signed for Ginzburg by G. William Miller, U.S. Secretary of the Treasury, on board a Concord plane to New York. The bill can be found among other Memorabilia.
Oversize material, along with many awards to Ginzburg and prison rules, includes a remarkable print given to Arina Ginzburg during her vacation on the Black Sea coast while Ginzburg was in prison by a group of young men who lived nearby. The painting depicts a mother with two sons surrounded by listening ears and watching eyes hidden everywhere. It turned out later that these men were KGB people spying on Arina, and the painting was to remind her that she was under constant surveillance.
Collection Contents
- Biographical file, 1936-2007.; 5 boxes (Box 1-4, 30)
  Includes trial and release material, certificates, identification documents, awards, references, applications, contracts, employment records, press releases, clippings, petitions, and family papers.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Confinement, exile and rehabilitation, 1960-2003; undated (Folder 1: 1-5)
    - First imprisonment, 1960-1962; 1991 (Folder 1: 1)
      Includes KGB files (photocopies), trial material, petitions to the Office of Prosecutor General (General'nomu prokuroru Sovetskogo Soiuza), and prison release certificate.
    - Second imprisonment, 1967-1972; 2003. (Folder 1: 1)
      Includes release certificate, prison's physician recollections, photographs, and other documents
    - Exile to Tarusa, 1974-1976. (Folder 1: 1)
      Includes register of Ginzburg's absences from Tarusa and draft complaint about falsification of surveillance order.
    - Third imprisonment, 1977-1979; bulk 1978. (Folder 1: 2-4)
      Includes statement of Petr Vins (Evangelical Christians - Baptists) protesting the arrest of Aleksandr Ginzburg, photographs, and unpublished typescripts about Ginzburg's trial by Vera Lashkova and Arina Ginzburg, with Arina Ginzburg's press release.
    - Rehabilitation, 1992-1996; 2003,; undated. (Folder 1: 5)
      Certificate of rehabilitation and clippings relating to Ginzburg's imprisonment and exile.
  - Education, 1948-1965. (Folder 1: 6)
    Applications and references, certificate for excellence in studies, review of Ginzburg's student paper, university records, student ID card. See also oversize box 29.
  - Employment, 1955-2002; undated (Folder 1: 7-12; 30: 1-2; 2: 1-7)
    - Business and calling cards, undated (Folder 1: 7)
    - Soviet Union, 1955-1973. (Folder 1: 8)
      Includes employment records (trudovaia knizhka), references, and employment contract with AndreĬ Sakharov.
    - France, 1981-2001; bulk 1981-1982. (Folder 1: 9)
      Includes contracts, work permits, correspondence
    - Lecture tour of American universities, 1979-1980s. (Folder 1: 10-12; 30: 1-2)
      Includes subject list, booklets, programs, announcements, correspondence, and clippings
    - Press cards, 1958-2001; bulk 1990s. (Folder 2: 1)
      Russian and French press cards, including Russkaia mysl', Soiuz zhurnalistov Rossii, and International Press
    - Publishing projects, 2002. (Folder 2: 4)
      Material relating to possible publication of "Gorizontal," "Evropeets," and "Vertikal'" newspapers
    - Russkaia mysl' documents, 21997-1998. (Folder 2: 5-7)
      Includes holograph t letters by Aleksandr and Arina Ginzburg, publications, and letters (mostly photocopies) protesting their dismissal from the newspaper editorial board
  - Family, 1968-1985 (Folder 2: 8-12)
    - Ginzburg, Arina, 1968-1972. (Folder 2: 8-10)
      Log book, address book, and other documents printed from CD 4 in ELECTRONIC DOCUMENTS (available on reading room workstation)
    - Ginzburg, Arina and Liudmila Ginzburg (mother of Aleksandr Ginzburg), 1980-1985. (Folder 2: 11)
      Identification and travel documents and social security cards
    - Shibaev, SergeĬ (Ginzburg's adopted son), 1979. (Folder 2: 12)
      Public statement and petitions to Soviet and U.S. authorities, legal documents and letters in support of Shibaev's emigration with the Ginzburgs. Photocopies
  - Household, 1986-2001 and undated. (Folder 3: 1-3)
    Includes financial accounts, petitions, address and phone books, documents relating to undeclared currency case against Aleksandr Ginzburg
  - Identification, membership, and travel, 1936-2001. (Folder 3: 4-6)
    Includes birth certificate, passports, trade union card, residence and travel permits, visas, asylum status card
  - Public attention and support, 1966-2007. (Folder 3: 7-12, 4: 1-2, 30: 3-4)
    - Alexander Ginzburg Defense Committee, 1977-1979. (Folder 3: 7-8)
      Includes list of members, appeals to Soviet and U.S. authorities, press releases, interviews, publications, nine photographic prints depicting a demonstration in defense of Ginzburg
    - Awards and invitations, 1972-1998. (Folder 3: 9)
      See Oversize box 29
      - Invitations, 1972-1998. (Folder 3: 9)
        Includes invitations from Jacques Chirac, the International Society for Human Rights (Frankfurt, Germany), Jean-Paul Bucher (to lunch with Mikhail Gorbachev), Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn (to Nobel Prize ceremony), Russian embassy in France
      - Awards, 1977-1980. (Folder 3 :9)
        Includes National Coalition of American Nuns Award and Key to Jersey City press kit.
        Key in oversize box 29
    - Publicity, 1966-2007 (Folder 3: 10-12, 4: 1-2, 30: 3-4)
      - APF news agency clippings relating to the trials of Ginzburg, his exile, and emigration of his family, 1968-1980, bulk 1977-1979, and undated (Folder 3: 10)
      - "Etikh liudeĬ ia brosit' ne mogu,", 2007. (Folder 3: 11)
        Publication honoring Ginzburg in newspaper 30 oktiabria, no. 71
      - French press clippings, 1966-1970. (Folder 3 :12)
        Relate to the trial of Ginzburg and Yuri Galanskov. Includes Posev article about Dubrovlag camp system
      - Russian and foreign press clippings, 1988-2002. (Folder 4: 1)
        Include transcript of the Radio Liberty memorial program, Novoe russkoe slovo article on confiscation of a copy of Doctor Zhivago, and "Memorial" society biographical dictionary entry
      - U.S. press clippings, 1979 and undated (Folder 4: 2)
      - World wide press clippings, 1990-1999. (Folder 30: 3-4)
- Correspondence, 1967-2005.; 2 boxes (Box 4-5)
  Divided into three groups: general correspondence of Arina and Aleksandr Ginzburg, their correspondence as editors of the Russkaia mysl' newspaper, and correspondence collected from other correspondents and arranged alphabetically therein.
  - General correspondence, Aleksandr and Arina Ginzburg, 1961-2005 and undated (Folder 4 :3-17, 5: 1-3)
    - Unidentified, 1971-1991 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Aizenberg, A., 1979 Aizova, Elena, 1981 Amal'rik, AndreĬ and Giuzel', 1973-1974 Astrakhan, Michelle, 1984 Aucouturier, Michel, 1995 (Folder 4: 4)
    - Bakhmin, Viacheslav and AndreĬ, and Bakhmina (Khromova) Tat'iana, 1980-2002; undated. (Folder 4: 5)
      Includes family photographs and sketch portraits of Soviet dissidents
    - Bogoraz, Larisa, 1968-1970 and undated Borisova, Tat'iana, 1990s BukovskiĬ, Vladimir, 1967-1997 and undated Burmistrovich, Il'ia, 1991 (Folder 4: 6)
      Includes memorandum from the KGB to the Central Committee of the KPSS regarding the case of Ginzburg, Galanskov, Dobrovol'skiĬ, and Lashkova and excerpts from the case file, 1967
    - Chirac, Jacques, 1993 Chuprinin, SergeĬ, 1997 Daniel', IUliĬ, 1970-1971 and 1977. Davydov, Egor, and Valeriia Davydova (Isakova), 1978 Dodin, Lev, circa 1994 (Folder 4: 7)
      Includes 1 photographic print depicting MaĬia Litvinova and Arina Ginzburg visiting IUliĬ Daniel' in exile (Kaluga), 1971
    - Feigina, Inna, 1991 Finzer, David R., 1985 Gaenko, Vladimir, and Nina and Tat'iana Gaenko, 1981-2000 Galanskov, Yuri, 1969 April Gal'perin, IUriĬ, 1988. Gerstenmaier, Cornelia Irena, 1988 (Folder 4: 8)
      See related photographs in PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Ginzburg, Liudmila, 1969-1971. (Folder 4: 9)
      See PHOTOGRAPHS for letters written on the back of photographic prints
    - Gorbanevskaia, Natal'ia, 1968-1971. (Folder 4: 10)
      See ELECTRONIC DOCUMENTS at the reading room workstation
    - Grigorenko, Petr, 1971-1976, and undated Gudava, Eduard, 1990 IAnovskaia, Lydiia, 2001 Il'ina, Emiliia, 2000 Iofe, Lidiia and Veniamin, 1971-1987 Ivanov, NikolaĬ Viktorovich, 1971. (Folder 4: 11)
      Includes photographs
    - Kalnyn'sh, Viktor, 1969 Kaminskaya, Dina (Ginzburg's lawyer), 1969 Kataeva-Lytkina, Nadezhda (Dom-muzei Mariny Tsvetaevoi), 1992 Kheifets, Mikhail, 1982, 1986 Kishilova, Anna, 2002 Krakhmal'nikova, Zoia, 1988 Krymova, Natalia and DmitriĬ Krymov, circa 1987 KublanovskiĬ, IUriĬ, 1985 Kuznetsov, Eduard, 1996 (Folder 4: 12)
    - Landa, Mal'va (from exile), 1978 Lashkova, Vera, 1981, 2005. Latynina, Alla, and Leonid Latynin, 1989-1990 Levitin-Krasnov, AnatoliĬ, 1971 Litvinov, Pavel, after 1981 (Folder 4: 13)
      Includes a photograph depicting Vera Lashkova, description of Nadezhda Mandel'shtam death, and photographs depicting reburial of Yuri Galanskov in August 1991 and a photo of Ginzburg and Leonid Latynin in Paris, 1990
    - Maksimov, Vladimir, 1986 Mémorial Caen Normandie (Museum), 2000-2002 MikhaĬlova, Natal'ia, and Boris MikhaĬlov, 1982 and undated Morgulis, Mikhail, 1985 Murzhenko, Liubov', 1980 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Nezmer, Pavel and Pavel Poliakov(?), 1996 Nosov, Aleksandr, 1992 Orlova, Kseniia Ivanovna (Khakhaev's mother), 1971-1972 Otten, NikolaĬ Davydovich, 1971 Panina, Issa, 1990. Pasmur, Aleksandr, 1978 Peltier-Zamoiska, Hélène, 1987 Pernin, Jean-François, 1982 Petrov, A. 1971 Podrabinek, Aleksandr, 1985 Pravda (newspaper), 1961 March Pressel, Joe, 1977 (Folder 4: 15)
      Includes clipping from Le Figaro and memorandum from Igor BrodetskiĬ of Voice of America
    - Radygina, Alla, 1985 Riazantsev, Mikhail, undated Ronkina, Irina, and ValeriĬ Ronkin, 1980. Rovner, Arkady, 1980 Rozenzweig, Yuri (IUriĬ), 1987 Rubanova, Irina (Leonid Pazhitnov's wife), 1991 January Russian Library of the Zionist Forum, 1996 (Folder 4: 16)
      See audiotape #41 in box 18 in SOUND AND VIDEO RECORDINGS
    - Saakiants, Anna, 1992, 1998 Sakharov, AndreĬ Dmitrievich, undated Sarkisian, David, undated. Shabalina, Sonia (Jerusalem), on behalf of Natan Shcharansky, 1999 Shakhovskaia, Zinaida, Paris, 1996 Simis, Konstantin, 1981 Smolkin, ValeriĬ 1985. (Folder 4: 17)
      Includes photographs of Ariadna Efron and David Sarkisian
    - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr, undated Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr, and Natal'ia Solzhenitsyna, 1970-2005, bulk 1990-2000, and undated (Folder 5: 1)
    - Solzhenitsyna, Natal'ia, 1980-2002. (Folder 5: 2)
      Includes letter from Ignat Solzhenitsyn. Printed from DVD in ELECTRONIC DOCUMENTS, box 13. Available at the reading room computer station
    - Stango, Antonio (chairman of the Italian Helsinki Committee), 1988 Tserkovno-obshchestvennyi vestnik, ca 1990s Verkholiak, DmitriĬ (Dmytro), 1971 Vigdorova, Frida, 1965 May Vladimova (Kuznetsova), Natal'ia, 1991, 199 Volkov, Oleg, and Margarita Volkova, 1990 and undated Yarim-Agaev, Yuri, and IUliia Pessina, 1981 Zernova, Ruth (Ruf?), 1984-1985 Ziman(?), Galina, undated (Folder 5: 3)
  - Russkaia mysl' correspondence of Aleksandr and Arina Ginzburg, 1980-1999 and undated (Folder 5: 4-9)
    - Anonymous, 1980s Agursky, Mikhail, 1982 AĬgi, GennadiĬ, 1989 Alekseeva, Liudmila, Valentin Turchin, and Yuri Yarim-Agaev, 1982 AleshkovskiĬ, IUz, 1992 and undated Babenyshev, Aleksandr, 1988 Babenysheva, Sara, 1982 Batchan, Aleksandr, 1986 Bobyshev, DmitriĬ, 1982 Brodsky, Joseph, 22 October 1987 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Chalidze, ValeriĬ, undated Dobkin, Alexander I., 1997 Dovlatov, SergeĬ, 1980 Egides, Petr, undated Eliseenko, Valentin, 1994 Etkind, Efim, 1981 Gabovich, EvgeniĬ, 1982 Gasferov, Aleksandr, 1982 Gladilina, Mariia, undated Glucksmann, F., 2000 Gordon, Ernest, 1985 Gunderson, Dorann, 1986 Igrunov, V. V., 1997 Juraitene, Natal'a, undated (Folder 5: 5)
    - Kaminskaia, Dina, 1981 Kestutis, Jakubinas, 1984 Konson, Lev, 1984 KublanovskiĬ, IUriĬ, 1982, 1985. Kuznetsov, Eduard, 1982 Lecomte, Bernard (Association des Journalistes France-Russie), 2000 LosskiĬ, Boris, 1994 (Folder 5: 6)
      Includes essay by KublanovskiĬ and a letter from Irina IlovaĬskaia of 15 December 1985
    - Maksimov, Vladimir, 1982 Milan, Claude, 1995. MiloslavskiĬ, IUriĬ, 1988 Mnukhin, Lev, 1994 Mukhametshin, Boris, 1985 Mychaltchouk, Wasyl', 1999. (Folder 5: 7)
      Includes a letter from Natal'ia Zelenko to Claude Milan, 1996